The woman known to history as Queen Mary I of
England was born on the 18th of February 1516
at Greenwich Palace just outside London.
Mary’s father was King Henry VIII of England, the
reigning monarch since 1509 and just the second
of the Tudor dynasty which had been established in
1485 by Henry’s father, King Henry VII. Her mother
was Queen Catherine of Aragon, the first wife of
Henry VIII, and a daughter of King Ferdinand
II of Aragon and Queen Isabella I of Castile,
the two monarchs whose marriage in 1469 would
eventually bring about the union of Aragon and
Castile into the Kingdom of Spain. Mary was the
first healthy baby born from Henry and Catherine’s
marriage, she having suffered multiple stillbirths
and miscarriages since they were wed in 1509.
The circumstances of Mary’s birth and the
political events of the years that followed would
shape her entire life. Her grandfather, King Henry
VII, had seized the throne of England back in 1485
after defeating King Richard III at the Battle
of Bosworth Field. With hindsight we can say that
this brought the Wars of the Roses, the series
of civil wars that had wracked England since
the 1450s, to an end. During these the Houses of
York and Lancaster had vied for the crown after
the mental collapse of King Henry VI from the
early 1450s onwards created a political crisis.
Eventually Henry Tudor, a Welsh upstart
with a quite tenuous claim to the throne,
had won out in 1485. Yet several major revolts
occurred in the late 1480s and into the 1490s
and there was no guarantee that the Tudor
dynasty would not be overthrown in time
just as Henry VI and Richard III had been. This
made the task of producing a male heir that would
ensure a smooth succession all the greater
in the eyes of Mary’s father, Henry VIII.
While women were not legally disbarred
from succeeding to the throne in England,
it would still be considered very much a
last resort for Mary to become queen one day.
Her entire early life would be shaped by her
father’s quest to acquire a male heir.
When Mary born in 1516, Catherine was only
thirty and Henry was in his mid-twenties.
The assumption was that a male heir would arrive
eventually. Consequently, during her earlier years
the king and his ministers were more
concerned about who Mary would marry one day.
At the time, England held the balance of power
in Western Europe between Spain and France,
who were engaged in a long-running conflict
for hegemony over the Italian peninsula.
The logic of English diplomacy was that Mary
would marry either a French or Spanish prince
to cement an alliance with one side or the other.
She was first betrothed to the Dauphin of France
at just two years old, an engagement which,
like several others made in the ensuing years,
was abandoned when alliances shifted once again.
At the age six, Mary was betrothed to her
cousin, the Holy Roman Emperor, Charles V,
who was sixteen years her senior, in order
to cement Henry’s alliance with the Emperor
against the King of France. Just four years
later, fortunes would shift once again,
when Charles married Isabella of Portugal
instead, an act which enraged Henry.
Mary would have been blissfully unaware of
these diplomatic negotiations during her youth.
Catherine herself supervised Mary’s early
education, providing foundational religious
instruction, teaching her daughter to speak
French and Spanish as fluently as English,
as well as learning Latin, the language
of the Roman Catholic Church and one
in which many books were still being
produced during the sixteenth century.
Mary was also instructed in music and
dance, both of which, like her parents,
she showed a talent for. At four years old, she
honoured a delegation from the King of France with
a performance on the virginal, a forerunner of the
harpsichord. Catherine’s own experience of having
a strong mother like Isabella of Castile, a great
military commander and queen in her own right,
almost certainly influenced her approach
to raising and educating her daughter.
It is perhaps partly because her mother did
not doubt that Mary could be Queen, that Mary
herself acquired the confidence and conviction
of her right to succeed to the throne one day.
Mary’s father also adored his daughter, lavishing
frequent gifts on her, and referring to her as “my
pearl in the world.” Mary resembled her father in
some respects. She had the same fair complexion,
pale blue eyes and ruddy cheeks. Like
him, she also loved music and dancing.
When Mary was nine years old, in 1525, her
father, still lacking a legitimate son,
made her the de facto Princess of Wales, vaguely
confirming that she was heir to the throne of
England. He sent her to Ludlow Castle in the
Welsh marches to “rule” Wales in his name,
and to complete her education. This practice was
typical for a king-in-waiting, but some historians
emphasize the fact that, while Mary was treated
in every other way as the heir to the throne,
she was never officially invested with the title
of Princess of Wales, which no woman in English
history had then ever held in her own right.
This lack of formal investiture indicates that
Henry did not really intend that Mary should
be Queen and still planned to have a son.
However, the decision to send her to Wales and
provide her with her own independent household
for the first time indicates that the king
was making contingency plans at the same time
should a male heir not arrive. Catherine,
after all, was nearly forty years old by then
and her child-bearing years
would soon be behind her.
Henry, a spendthrift monarch who completely
reversed the sound economic footing his father
had placed the English state on, spent generously
on outfitting Mary’s household at Ludlow,
with everything needed to advertise her
position as heir to the throne of England.
There was a throne in Mary’s presence chamber,
where she received ambassadors, dignitaries and
petitioners on her father’s behalf in Wales.
Cloth-of-gold covered the altar in Mary’s chapel
at Ludlow and a staff of literally dozens served
at her court. Yet historians have noted that Henry
spent about the same amount of money annually
on the household of his illegitimate son, Henry
Fitzroy, born in 1519 to one of his mistresses,
Elizabeth Blount, whom the king had also made
Duke of Richmond and Somerset. Some, therefore,
still consider it an open question as to whether
Henry might have been toying in the 1520s and for
much of the 1530s with the idea of trying to leave
his throne to Richmond, despite his illegitimacy.
In any event, Richmond died in 1536 of
what may have been tuberculosis.
What was perhaps especially strange about the
concerns about Mary succeeding as Queen of England
was that King Henry II, King Edward IV and
Mary’s own grandfather, King Henry VII,
had all claimed to have inherited a legitimate
right to rule from female forebears. Henry VII
had simultaneously borrowed his legitimacy from
his wife, Elizabeth of York, and his mother,
Margaret Beaufort. Most scholars, therefore,
assume that Henry VIII, in the absence of a son,
intended that his daughter would be Queen, but
that her power would be exercised primarily by her
husband, until a male heir of hers came of age, as
precedent dictated. Matters changed though in the
second half of the 1520s after Anne Boleyn,
the daughter of a leading English diplomat,
Sir Thomas Boleyn, won the king’s attentions at
court. Increasingly disenchanted with his wife,
Henry became infatuated with Anne. For
her part, Boleyn played a long game and
refused to let Henry enter her bed for
a very long time, arguing with the king
that she would not enter a relationship with him
until he gave serious consideration to obtaining
a divorce from Catherine and then marrying her. If
he made her Queen of England, Anne assured Henry,
she would give him the male heir he so
longed for to secure the Tudor dynasty.
So began what would soon become known both
in England and at the courts of Europe
as the ‘The King’s Great Matter’, his quest to
obtain a divorce from Mary’s mother Catherine.
While the Protestant Reformation was already
underway across Europe and was sundering the
ties between some kingdoms and states with the
Papacy in Rome, England was still very much within
the Roman Catholic fold in the 1520s. If Henry
wanted a divorce he had to provide evidence of
a clear legal basis for doing so to Pope Clement
VII in Rome. Soon an annulment to the marriage was
being sought on the grounds that Henry’s union
with Catherine had broken biblical law, because
she had briefly been married to his older brother
Arthur, who had died in 1502. Henry and Catherine
had received a papal dispensation to be wed, when
he became king, because Catherine had claimed that
the brief marriage to Prince Arthur had never
been consummated. Now, nearly two decades later,
Henry claimed he was after having an attack
of conscience and needed to divorce Catherine
as he had breached the injunction of the book
of Leviticus in the Old Testament which stated,
“If any man should take his brother’s wife, it is
an unclean thing….they will be childless.”
In 1527, Henry secretly made his first overtures
concerning the divorce to Pope Clement VII.
Unfortunately for Henry, Emperor Charles V’s
armies had sacked and occupied Rome right around
this time. Charles was Queen Catherine’s nephew
and there was no way a Papal dispensation for
Henry to divorce Catherine would be forthcoming
from Rome so long as the city was in Spanish
hands. In any event, even when the situation
in Rome changed in the years that followed,
Clement would not prove to be receptive to Henry’s
overtures for a divorce. Thus, Henry would spend
the next several years pursuing his ‘Great Matter’
through various legal, academic and theological
arguments. Eventually he would take the dramatic
decision to split with Rome altogether and declare
himself to be the Supreme Head of the Church in
England. In this way he was able to sanction his
own divorce from Catherine in 1533 and marry
Anne Boleyn almost immediately thereafter.
These moves also opened the floodgates for
Protestant reformers like the new Archbishop of
Canterbury, Thomas Cranmer, to begin introducing
wide-ranging religious reforms to England.
All of these initiatives had consequences
for Mary between 1527 and 1533. In 1528,
Henry recalled her from Ludlow to the court. Her
recall at this time to London suggests that her
father mistakenly anticipated that he would soon
acquire his divorce, marry Anne and produce a son,
in which case it would be better to not have Mary
at Ludlow performing the duties of a Princess of
Wales. Yet, although Henry would have known
that his divorce would have the consequence
of making Mary legally illegitimate, he did
not immediately demote her in any other way.
Perhaps this was simply for practicality’s sake.
After all, Henry could not be certain that he
would get his divorce, or that Anne would give
birth to a son once they were married. Hence, even
as Henry pursued the divorce which would make his
daughter illegitimate, she remained Princess Mary,
her servants continued to wear her badges,
and Henry continued to support her household
financially. The ensuing years were painful
and humiliating for both Catherine and Mary.
Mother and daughter were subjected to tales of
Henry’s intimacy with Anne at court and Henry
continued to browbeat Catherine for denying that
her marriage to Arthur had been consummated,
demanding that she agree to dissolve the marriage.
Catherine refused, asserting that their marriage
was valid and that she was rightly the Queen
of England by God’s will. In retaliation,
Henry forbade her to see or communicate with
Mary until she submitted to Henry’s will.
Cut off from her mother and uncertain of her fate
at her father’s hands, fifteen-year-old Mary’s
health began to suffer. She experienced irregular
menstrual patterns and bouts of crippling
depression. It is unclear what caused these
symptoms. Given her later health issues, which
we will return to, these were most likely the
first signs of some reproductive health issues.
Alternatively, it may have been the general
stress of the situation she found herself in
as little more than a child of 12 or
13 from the end of the 1520s onwards.
Compounding this was Henry’s drift towards the
small but growing Protestant camp within England,
something which both Catherine and Mary,
as devout Roman Catholics, found doubly
troubling on top of the divorce proceedings.
Henry himself was a doctrinal Catholic,
but he was an exceptionally impressionable
monarch and as Protestant reformers like Cranmer
counselled him on how to obtain his divorce, they
also managed to convince him of the reasonableness
of some of the new Protestant ideas that were
arriving to England from the continent.
In January 1531, Henry received a communication
from the Pope ordering him to separate from Anne
until Rome had made its final decision on
the proposed annulment of his first marriage.
In response the king addressed
the English Parliament in February
and made clear his intentions to be recognized as
Supreme Head of the Church of England. Parliament
acquiesced in principle, and Henry’s new title
was proclaimed, but it would take a year and more
to obtain a final submission from England’s
clergy and many bishops and leading clerics were
removed from their positions when they refused to
acknowledge the Supremacy. As this played out Anne
had moved into Queen Catherine’s chambers and was
living as the de-facto queen. It cannot be doubted
that all of this hurt Mary deeply, both in terms
of her familial situation and her religious views.
One of the characteristics most often ascribed
to Mary Tudor is a remarkable piety and an overly
zealous devotion to Catholicism. However, it was
not until much later in life, that her engagement
with religion would increase to the point of
becoming especially noteworthy or extreme.
It is likely that her long separation from her
mother, and the pervasiveness of Protestant
reform in England’s halls of power, made her
cleave more closely to her Catholicism.
On the 25th of January 1533, nigh on seven
years after he had first begun pursuing her,
Henry VIII finally married Anne Boleyn in a
secret early morning ceremony in his private
chapel at Whitehall Palace. She was already
pregnant. Events then began to proceed apace,
as Henry and the newly created
Archbishop of Canterbury, Thomas Cranmer,
acted to consolidate Henry’s control of the
Church, to affirm England’s separation from Rome,
and to finalize his divorce from Catherine
of Aragon, who was now banished from court
and living at Kimbolton Castle in Cambridgeshire,
her health declining steeply at the same time.
In May of 1533, Cranmer declared the King’s first
marriage null and void and his marriage to Anne
as valid. This supposedly made the
now 17-year-old Mary illegitimate,
yet Henry did not immediately proceed to
declare her as such. In fact, she retained
her title and her father’s financial support
for her household during the ensuing months.
On the 1st of June, Anne Boleyn was crowned
Queen of England, and on the 7th of September
she gave birth to her and Henry’s first child.
Much to the king’s dismay it was a girl,
whom they named Elizabeth. Henry proclaimed,
quote, “by God’s grace, boys will follow.”
Several weeks after Elizabeth’s birth,
Henry instructed that Mary’s title of
Princess should be revoked and henceforth
she should be referred to as “the Lady Mary.”
Her servants were told to remove her
royal badges and to wear only the king’s.
Sent to live in her new half-sister’s household,
she was allegedly mistreated there on Anne’s
orders in the period that ensued, though the
veracity of these claims is still disputed.
Moreover, some of her difficulties were brought
upon herself by Mary. She refused to acknowledge
the legitimacy of her father’s new marriage and
part of the treatment of her during these years
was clearly designed to pressure her into making
a public statement of support for the new queen.
In this environment a chilly relationship
developed between king and daughter in the
mid-1530s. In many ways it was a very familial
affair. Mary, who would be twenty before long,
was proving to be as hard-headed as her
father. Under these conditions her health
worsened further and she also became more
devout, taking comfort from daily prayer.
The following three years were full of both
religious and dynastic upheaval. In March of 1534,
the Act of Succession was introduced in
Parliament, followed later in the year by
the institution of the Oath of Succession, the Act
of Supremacy, and the Treason Act. Taken together,
these measures delegitimized Henry’s marriage
to Catherine, legitimized his marriage to Anne,
set the seal on Henry’s power as head of the
Church of England, and decreed that denial
of any of this was a treasonable offence and
punishable by death. In January 1535, Henry’s
administration began to accelerate reforms by
dissolving England’s religious houses and taking
them into crown possession. Henry didn’t agree to
this out of any movement towards Protestant views.
He was persuaded in this direction because it
led to an enormous cash windfall for the crown
through the fire-sale of over 800 religious houses
and their estates. Some prominent individuals
resisted these revolutionary changes. Among them
was the English Lord Chancellor, Sir Thomas More,
who was executed for treason for his refusal
to acknowledge Henry’s split with Rome. Mary
also refused to acknowledge her father’s supremacy
over the church. She would have been encouraged,
all the same, by the sudden fall of Anne Boleyn.
She suffered two miscarriages in quick succession
after the birth of Elizabeth and by November
1535 Henry’s attention had already wandered
to Anne’s lady-in-waiting, Jane Seymour.
Anne’s days as queen were numbered.
On the 7th of January 1536, Mary’s mother,
Catherine of Aragon died. Some who hated
Anne Boleyn for usurping Catherine’s place
whispered of poison, but Catherine’s health had,
in fact, been steadily worsening for several
years and she most likely died of cancer.
Mary was forbidden to attend her mother’s funeral.
Catherine’s death was devastating for her. In its
aftermath she began writing to her cousin, Emperor
Charles V, continuing the case which her mother
had pressed to him from afar for so many years.
However, things changed rather dramatically.
Only a few months later, Anne was accused of
adultery and treason, imprisoned in the Tower,
and then executed. With this, the now 20-year-old
Mary’s fortunes had seemingly changed for the
better and she wrote to her father seeking
to reconcile. Here she asked to be allowed to
return to court, to serve Jane Seymour, who
Henry had quickly taken as his third queen.
Mary, though, received a cold reply from
Henry’s by now all-powerful chief minister,
Thomas Cromwell, that the king still demanded that
Mary submit to him regarding the Act of Supremacy.
Mary wrote desperately to Cromwell that she had,
quote, “done the utmost that her conscience would
suffice.” Cromwell replied that if such were the
case, then Henry would most likely not allow her
to return to court in any fashion. In the end,
convinced that she now had no other choice,
Mary relented and on the surface acknowledged
the religious changes that had been carried out
in recent time, despite the manner in which
they clashed with her ardent Catholicism.
Mary’s circumstances improved markedly after she
returned to court. Henry was happy to welcome her
back and father and daughter gradually reconciled.
Henry gave Mary splendid chambers at court,
as well as princely accommodations at the country
estates of Hunsdon, Beaulieu, and Hatfield.
A warm relationship also developed between
Mary and her new stepmother, Jane Seymour,
who is often credited with helping to
restore Henry’s two daughters to favour.
The relationship between Mary and Elizabeth would
change too over time. Previously, Mary had not
been able to develop much sisterly affection
for the half-sister who had replaced her,
and the 17-year age gap between them did little
to encourage their closeness. But Elizabeth’s
de-legitimization effectively made the two sisters
equals, both the “natural” daughters of a king,
equally excluded from the line of succession.
This likely made it easier for Mary to develop
a closer and less complicated relationship with
Elizabeth as the latter grew up in the 1540s.
All England rejoiced as well on the 12th
of October 1537 when Queen Jane gave birth
to the long desired male heir, Prince Edward.
Being supplanted by a male heir was much easier
for Mary to accept, since it was the accepted
convention. The return to something approaching
a normal family life was seen in her standing
as godmother to Prince Edward. Sadly, though,
Jane Seymour died of puerperal fever, then known
as childbed fever, within two weeks of giving
birth to her son. Mary served as chief mourner at
her stepmother’s funeral.
Henry mourned Jane’s death deeply and would not
marry again for two years. By 1539, negotiations
were underway for the king’s marriage to Anne of
Cleves, a German principality in the Rhineland.
Mary was now 23 years old. Her life was
considerably happier and more stable
than it had been in years. One thing which had
not changed, though, was her unmarried state.
As the king’s daughter, she could not be
married to an Englishman below her station,
and if a foreign prince were to be the solution,
the problem arose of who she should marry
in order to cultivate a foreign alliance
for England. When Henry’s marriage to Anne
of Cleves was being negotiated, a simultaneous
offer was made for Mary’s hand by Anne’s cousin,
Duke Philip of Bavaria. In December of 1539, the
Duke arrived quietly in England. Mary and Philip
met in the gardens at Westminster Abbey where they
got to know each other. Philip soon expressed his
eagerness to marry, despite their religious
incompatibility, as Philip was a Protestant.
Mary indicated her willingness to consider
the match if it was what her father wished,
but the proposal was foiled by the swift
annulment of Henry’s marriage to Anne of Cleves.
This was contracted on the continent before they
ever met and when Anne finally arrived to England,
Henry was not happy with his new wife, claiming
the court painter, Hans Holbein, who had been sent
to Germany to paint a picture of Anne for the king
to view back in England, had flattered her in his
depiction. Henry immediately sought an annulment
to the marriage bonds that had been exchanged
between Anne and Henry’s representatives
in Germany, one which was quickly granted.
In tandem Henry abandoned plans to wed his
daughter to Duke Philip. Strangely, Anne continued
to live in England afterwards and she and Mary
developed a close enough relationship.
In July of 1540, before the ink was even dry on
his annulment, Henry married as his fifth wife
Catherine Howard, a 17-year-old niece of the Duke
of Norfolk, the senior-most noble in England.
Mary found it difficult to get
along with her fourth step-mother.
Catherine was nine years younger than Mary herself
and their personalities were very different.
The new queen was high-spirited, vivacious and, to
Mary’s mind, rather immature. Queen Catherine soon
began to complain to King Henry, that Lady Mary
did not show her enough respect, and Mary absented
herself from court more frequently. Mary was also
somewhat aggrieved, like many others at court,
at the manner in which Thomas Cromwell had been
swiftly removed from power and executed on Henry’s
orders after the Cleves alliance collapsed and
the Duke of Norfolk, Cromwell’s inveterate enemy
in government, engineered the marriage of his
niece to the king. While Cromwell had been central
to organizing Henry’s divorce from Mary’s mother
nearly a decade earlier, Mary and he had developed
a friendly relationship in the years that
followed and there were even rumours at the time
that Cromwell was scheming to marry Henry’s
daughter. That plan, if it ever really existed,
came to naught, as Cromwell was executed on
the 28th of July 1540.
Mary had a great deal more reason to resent her
father the following year when Henry reacted to
a potential coup with the execution of nearly an
entire family of cousins to the Tudors, the Poles.
Margaret Pole, the Countess of Salisbury, was
the daughter of the long-dead George Plantagenet,
Duke of Clarence, a younger brother of King Edward
IV who had ruled England between 1461 and 1483
in the midst of the Wars of the Roses. Margaret’s
family was amongst the few descendants of the old
House of York that remained after the Wars of
the Roses. Each of her four sons represented a
potential rival claimant to the throne. Moreover,
the Poles were fervently Roman Catholic. When the
Protestant reforms had advanced to the point of
Henry’s excommunication from the Church, a faction
began to form around one scion of the family,
Reginald Pole, who was then living in Italy,
to raise him to the throne. Pole had been made
a Cardinal of the Roman Catholic Church in 1536.
In the period that followed, Henry made every
effort to have Cardinal Pole sent back to England.
When he failed, the king instead ordered
the arrest of his relatives in England.
Then, in one of Henry’s most disreputable acts,
he ordered the execution of the Cardinal’s
67-year old mother and two of her sons, as
well as imprisoning her grandson, who died,
most likely of starvation, within a year. Mary
was deeply grieved by Lady Salisbury’s execution,
as Margaret had been Mary’s governess for
many years in her childhood. The two women
had remained close in subsequent years. In years
to come Mary would seek to bring the Poles,
or what remained of the family, back into the
fold in England. In the early 1540s when all
of this occurred, though, she could do little
but swallow whatever resentments she felt.
Henry ordered the execution of his fifth wife,
Catherine Howard, for adultery and treason
in February of 1542. Less than a year later,
he married his sixth wife, Catherine Parr.
Like Jane Seymour before him, Catherine
Parr made efforts to be a loving stepmother
to all three of Henry’s children, and
encouraged a close family environment.
While it might have been difficult for Mary
to regard Catherine Parr as a maternal figure,
since Catherine was only three years older
than herself, the two had known one another
for several years and got along well. Both
women were highly educated. Catherine is
often credited with influencing Henry to restore
his daughters fully to the line of succession,
for which Mary was deeply grateful. Meanwhile,
Henry’s declining health over the next years
made Mary realize that soon the man that held this
strange family together would be gone and that the
differences between herself and her siblings
might be harder to reconcile in future.
Henry VIII died on the 28th of January 1547.
Three days later his nine-year-old son from his
brief marriage to Jane Seymour was proclaimed
as King Edward VI. He was just nine years old
and so a regency council would rule on
his behalf until the boy came of age.
Henry was generous to his children in his
will. He left vast estates and movable property
to both of his daughters and explicitly
recognized their places in the succession.
If Edward died without an heir, Mary would
succeed him first, and lacking any issue herself,
the throne would then pass to Elizabeth. Henry
also left Mary extensive estates in East Anglia,
including lands in the counties of Norfolk,
Suffolk and Essex. Mary now headed her own
independent household, an extremely rare state
for an unmarried woman, even a princess.
Henry’s children drifted apart from one another
after his death. Mary rarely came to court,
preferring to live quietly on her estates in
East Anglia, rather than witness the advance
of a radical new Protestant regime as the Seymour
family and others at court such as the Archbishop
of Canterbury, Thomas Cranmer, now began to
implement a more thoroughgoing Reformation.
Henry had been a Catholic in virtually all
respects. He had simply tolerated the Protestants
in his government as they had facilitated the
organization of his divorce back in the 1530s.
However, the 1540s had seen a Catholic backlash
against the Protestants. Now they were free
to respond in turn and Cranmer and others were
determined to make England a Protestant nation
once Edward succeeded to the throne. In 1549,
Edward’s government passed the Act of Uniformity,
which abolished the Latin mass and
introduced the English Book of Common Prayer,
compiled by Cranmer, which prescribed a
new, Protestant church service in English.
Catholic processions, pilgrimages, and other
ceremonies were prohibited. The Act also called
for the removal of all Catholic-style display,
and in churches and abbeys across England,
stained glass windows were smashed, and crucifixes
and religious images were torn down and burnt.
From her estates away from court, Mary watched on
with some horror at the new attacks on the Roman
Catholic Church. She herself flouted the new
rules and continued to hear the mass in Latin,
frequently inviting Catholics to
join her. It was during this time
that Mary’s religious devotion began
to be remarked upon as extraordinary.
She reportedly began attending mass as many as
four times daily and spending hours at prayer.
At court Edward and his advisors soon resolved
to put a stop to his sister’s open practice of
Catholicism. He invited his two sisters to court
for Christmas in 1550, for a rare family reunion.
An exceptionally embarrassing episode occurred
during the celebrations, when the 13-year-old
Edward publicly chastised and denounced his
34-year-old sister in front of the whole court
for her disobedience in refusing to accept the new
religious dispensations. Then, a few weeks later,
Mary was summoned to appear at court once
again. She arrived with a large retinue,
every last one of her attendants visibly carrying
rosary beads. When Edward once again called upon
her to submit, she invoked the protection of her
cousin, Emperor Charles V. The Spanish ambassador
then stepped forward and threatened Edward with
diplomatic consequences should Lady Mary not be
permitted to practice her religion freely. Edward
was enraged, yet he backed down all the same,
grudgingly agreeing to allow Mary to continue to
hear the Latin mass, though only in private.
Mary had scored a great
victory, not just for herself,
but for Catholics across England, who were
encouraged and emboldened by her resistance.
It is important to remember when assessing these
events and what would happen throughout the 1550s
that Roman Catholics were still very much
in the majority in England and Wales.
The Protestants might have come to power
in London and at court, but they probably
accounted for no more than 10 to 20 percent of
the population during Edward’s reign. Hence Mary
became a symbol of Catholic resistance within the
royal family for many people. The struggle with
her brother no doubt called up terrible memories
of similar conflicts with her father and Mary
began to be afraid that she might have gone too
far. Fearful that Edward might now seize upon
any excuse to imprison her, Mary began plotting
in 1551 to flee from England to the continent by
enlisting the aid of her cousin, Emperor Charles
V, through the Spanish ambassador in London.
She came very close to doing so late that
summer, though eventually she decided against it
and resolved to remain in England. It would prove
before long to have been a very wise decision.
Contrary to the traditional
historical characterizations of him,
King Edward VI was not the weak and sickly
boy he has often been portrayed to be.
He was actually a strong, healthy, and athletic
boy, much like his father had been as a young man.
No one therefore had any serious expectation that
the boy would not grow up. However, during the
autumn of 1552, he suffered, in quick succession,
an attack of measles, and then one of smallpox.
These illnesses were catastrophic to his immune
system, and Edward subsequently became perilously
weak and sick. Fearing that he might die and
leave the English throne to his Catholic sister,
Edward agreed to a new plan for the royal
succession. This nullified the last wishes
of his father and formally excluded both of
his sisters from the succession. He observed
that his sisters were both illegitimate and should
not inherit the crown before stating that if
he died without issue he should be succeeded by
the 15-year-old Lady Jane Grey, the granddaughter
of Henry VIII’s youngest sister, Mary. At the
same time Edward’s condition worsened in the
spring and early summer of 1553. He had begun to
cough up blood and many historians believe that
he was now suffering from tuberculosis, though
it may have been a combination of conditions.
Knowing that his time was short, Edward
made plans to summon his sisters to court,
and sanctioned John Dudley, the Duke of
Northumberland, the real power behind the throne
who had plotted to make Lady Grey the new heir, to
capture and imprison them both when they arrived.
The goal was to ensure that Grey would
be proclaimed Queen without opposition.
Mary received Edward’s summons on the 2nd of
July 1553. She was aware that he had been ill,
but believed he was recovering. Therefore, when
she received his summons, she was not worried,
and departed for London with several retainers
the following day. Mary and her retinue only got
as far as Hertfordshire when they were intercepted
on the road by a supporter of Mary’s from court.
He had ridden hard to warn her of the trap
her brother had set for her, and informed her
that Edward was dying and was planning to place
the Protestant Lady Jane Grey on the throne.
Mary immediately turned around and rushed back
to East Anglia. Retreating to Framlingham Castle,
she began to mobilize her many supporters
there. She did not have long to prepare.
On the 6th of July 1553, 15-year-old
Edward died at Greenwich Palace
and Lady Jane Grey was quickly proclaimed as Queen
of England by the Duke of Northumberland. However,
she was never crowned, as within days the national
tide shifted overwhelmingly in Mary’s favour.
The Privy Council, seeing that Edward’s plan for
the succession was proving to be wildly unpopular,
transferred their support to Mary and
proclaimed her Queen on the 19th of July.
Mary rode into London on a wave of
support, while the unfortunate Jane Grey,
who was nothing more than a pawn in these
machinations, was placed in the Tower of London
and eventually executed in early 1554. The
Duke of Northumberland was placed on trial,
found guilty of treason and executed just
a month after Mary ascended as queen.
Mary’s accession to the throne was greeted with
a sense of both continuity and relief to many,
who had feared the excesses of her brother’s
religious reforms. Protestants on the other hand,
fearing the religious upheaval to come, began to
leave England for exile. Most historians identify
Mary’s major objectives as queen as being the
restoration of the Catholic faith in England,
something which could be secured in the long
run by her marriage, even in her late thirties,
and the production of a Catholic heir. These
were certainly cherished goals of hers,
but they were certainly not the only ones. In
her mind, and according to conventional wisdom,
they were foremost because nothing else could
be achieved in any lasting way without them.
Without an heir, she could have no
stability, and therefore could not
ensure that any reforms she might enact
would endure for decades to come.
The new Queen needed allies to work closely
with her in her new government and soon
brought figures like Thomas Howard, Duke
of Norfolk, and Bishop Stephen Gardiner,
who had been marginalized and persecuted
under Edward into her government.
Gardiner was made Bishop of Winchester, and Lord
Chancellor, and it was he who placed the crown on
Mary’s head at her coronation in Westminster Abbey
on the 1st of October 1553. Other initial measures
concerned the treasury. Mary came to the throne
when it was in a bleak state financially.
Her father’s spendthrift habits in the last
decade of his reign and enormously costly
wars with France had brought the country close
to bankruptcy. Currency debasement had followed.
Edward VI had been forced to continue debasement
of the coinage to maintain his own government
and by the time of his death English coins
were largely just copper coated in silver.
Mary decided on a two-pronged strategy to resolve
the fiscal problem, a budgetary retrenchment in
key departments, and a re-organization and
streamlining of the tax system. It would take
years, and Mary would not live to see better
days for the English economy, but she laid the
groundwork for an economic recovery in England
in the second half of the sixteenth century.
Mary was indeed her mother’s daughter and
comprehended a nation’s might in much the same way
as her Spanish royal forebears did. As such, she
was keen to promote the development of navigation
and exploration, particularly in pursuit of a
Northeast Passage, a sea route over the north
of Europe to Asia. To this end, Mary issued a
charter to the Muscovy Company in 1555, the first
joint-stock company in English history, under the
governorship of famed explorer Sebastian Cabot,
giving them a trading monopoly in Russia and
the Baltic region. She patronized cartographers
and navigators to produce maps and atlases,
and sponsored naval adventurers to sail south
to establish trade relationships with the
west coast of Africa. The Muscovy Company
soon established contacts with the Duchy of
Muscovy in Russia and began trading therewith,
an important early development in England’s
overseas colonial and commercial activity.
As the first real Queen Regnant of England, Mary
was in unfamiliar territory. The best course
seemed to be to go with conventional wisdom and
find a husband with whom she could produce an
heir. This was problematic in and of itself. Most
Englishmen occupied a station too low to wed the
Queen and the few eligible English Catholic nobles
proved unsuitable. Mary’s cousin, Charles V,
proposed marriage to his only son, Prince
Philip of Spain. A portrait of Prince Philip,
painted by the great Italian painter
Titian, was sent to Mary in late 1553.
Mary was said to have instantly fallen in love
with the young man in the portrait. This anecdote,
if true, reveals a part of Mary’s personality
that hitherto she had been forced to keep hidden,
her ardent desire to finally marry and start
a family after literally decades of turmoil
in which the subject of her marrying had
become enormously complicated. Now, finally,
Mary was Queen and could pursue marriage
on her own terms. Thus, at the age of 36,
she insisted on marrying the handsome Prince
Philip of Spain, who was eleven years younger
than herself at the time.
Mary’s choice of husband was very unpopular.
Most English people were deeply suspicious of
foreigners and feared that the ever-expanding
Spanish state, which controlled the Low
Countries and much of Italy in Europe,
and had an empire that spanned huge parts of
the Americas, would absorb England politically.
Indeed, Mary’s determination to wed the Spanish
prince sparked a rebellion in January 1554.
This originated in Kent and was led by Sir
Thomas Wyatt. During it 3,000 rebels marched
towards London with the intention of deposing
Mary and possibly placing Mary’s younger sister,
Elizabeth, on the throne, though Elizabeth
was not directly involved in the revolt. Mary
had fewer loyal supporters in the capital than
elsewhere in England and was forced to act quickly
to persuade London to act on her behalf. The
queen stood up before restive crowds at London’s
Guildhall on the 1st of February 1554 and gave
a rousing speech to galvanize support for her.
Thereafter London’s people acted decisively to bar
the city gates to the rebels. Mary’s subsequent
response was severe. Wyatt and many of the other
leaders of the revolt were executed. Elizabeth,
who insisted that she had not been involved in
the plot, was arrested and imprisoned in the
Tower for several months, but she was eventually
released. This whole episode made Mary even more
determined to marry Philip, though a Marriage
Act was issued by parliament in April 1554
through which it was stated that while Prince
Philip would bear the title “King of England”,
he would remain the more junior figure in their
marriage so far as English law went. Moreover,
if Mary were to predecease Philip without
their marriage having resulted in children,
Philip would have no claim to the throne,
which would instead pass to Elizabeth.
Mary finally met Philip for the first time at
Hampton Court Palace on the 23rd of July 1554.
She was strongly attracted to him, telling him
that she looked forward eagerly to their marriage.
One of Philip’s aides confided to a correspondent
that Philip did not find the now 37-year-old Mary
attractive at all, but obeyed his father’s
command to marry the Queen of England for
dynastic reasons and for the influence Spain
might now be able to exercise in England.
The two were married at Winchester Cathedral two
days later, on the 25th of July 1554. The wedding
emphasized Mary’s commitment to simplicity and
tradition. Rather than the fabulous display
typical of royal weddings, Mary’s was rather
simple. Her love of fine fashion was evident, with
the bride in a gown of purple and gold tissue,
but she wore a plain gold wedding band.
This period immediately after her
marriage was a happy one for Mary.
Little more than a month later, she began
to show signs of pregnancy, experiencing
morning sickness and gaining weight. In the
midst of this, on the 24th of November 1554,
Mary received her cousin, Cardinal Reginald
Pole, at court. After his long exile in Italy,
he had arrived home to England as the official
Papal Envoy, one who would help begin the process
of restoring England to the Roman Church. Cardinal
Pole greeted the Queen by quoting the Ave Maria.
In the Christian scriptures, the angel Gabriel
salutes the Virgin Mary with this prayer,
when delivering the news that she is pregnant
with the Christ child. Mary later reported that
as she listened to Cardinal Pole speak she
could feel her baby stirring in her womb.
In early modern Europe, even if a woman showed
symptoms of pregnancy, she was not considered
officially pregnant until she felt a “quickening,”
that is, until she felt the baby move inside her.
England rejoiced at news this had occurred
and Parliament promptly passed an act
designating Philip as regent for Mary’s heir
should she die in childbirth and the baby survive.
In April of 1555, Mary withdrew from
the court for her “confinement”,
about six weeks before her anticipated due date,
as was the tradition. Mary’s sister Elizabeth
was summoned to court to attend her sister,
along with numerous ladies and midwives.
The birthing chamber was an extremely rarefied
atmosphere, a world of women, not to be seen
by public eyes. Still, Mary could not resist
flaunting her joy, and on St. George’s Day,
soon after she entered her confinement, Mary
quite deliberately appeared at a window to
watch her husband lead the festivities, standing
in a side profile, so that the crowd could see her
big belly. England waited with bated breath for
the child who would inherit one of the greatest
royal legacies in European history – both the
throne of England and the Spanish Habsburg Empire.
On the 1st of June Mary complained of pain and
cramping and the midwives and court physicians
predicted the birth would occur within days, but
these came and went and still no baby was born.
The summer stretched on and Mary’s attendants
became more uneasy. As the summer passed,
and still no child was born, more and more people
began to doubt the Queen’s pregnancy and rumours
swirled around London. By late July, Mary’s belly
had begun to recede. There would be no baby.
It had been a “phantom pregnancy,” a very
rare condition in which a woman physically
manifests all the symptoms of pregnancy, yet
is not pregnant. It is usually caused by a
combination of both hormonal and psychological
factors. In this case Mary was most likely
experiencing serious health issues which caused
symptoms that were then interpreted as pregnancy.
From there her great desire for a child
convinced her that she was in fact pregnant.
On the 1st of August 1555, Mary quietly
exited her confinement and returned to court.
Philip was deeply disappointed that no child
had been born and, much to Mary’s grief,
he departed England soon after to
manage his affairs on the continent.
Abandoned by her husband and humiliated in
the eyes of her people, Mary grew despondent,
lapsing into depression. The possibility cannot
be denied that her despair and precarious mental
state might have influenced her
subsequent decisions and policies.
Mary was heard to blame her misfortunes on the
judgment of God, for her “toleration” and “mercy”
towards the Protestant heretics. It is perhaps
no accident then that the religious persecutions
under Mary’s government accelerated from the
summer of 1555 onwards, though some of this
can also be attributed to the influence
of Pole and others within the government.
The crackdown on the Protestant reforms of her
brother’s reign intensified in 1555 and 1556.
The Protestant measures of the 1530s and 1540s
were revoked. Mary retroactively declared her
parents’ marriage to have been valid after all.
She also revoked the 1549 Act of Uniformity
and ordered that the mass be once again celebrated
in Latin and churches redecorated in the Catholic
manner. Monasticism was revived, clerical celibacy
was re-established, and married clerics were
removed from their offices and ordered to leave
their wives. Roman Catholicism was restored after
what many would have perceived as the temporary
Protestant aberration of Edward’s reign.
This satisfied most English people, but more
conservative Catholics still wanted to abolish
the royal supremacy and return to the fold of the
Roman Catholic Church. Mary had not changed her
views on the Papal supremacy. The rapprochement
with Rome was a delicate negotiation, which would
take many months to complete and because she
needed their support, the settlement allowed
Mary’s wealthiest and most powerful subjects, who
had benefited from Henry VIII’s dissolution of the
monasteries, to keep the land and the abbeys that
had been taken from the Church. Philip insisted on
going further and Mary agreed that the old “heresy
laws” should be re-established. Accordingly,
in February 1555, as Mary eagerly anticipated her
first child, the first executions of Protestants
by burning at the stake, for which Mary would
become known above all else, were carried out.
When the heresy laws were reintroduced, the slow
trickle of Protestant exiles from England to
places like Protestant Geneva on the continent,
which had begun when Mary assumed the throne,
swelled. By 1558 over 800 Protestants had
left England and before Mary’s reign was over
approximately 280 would be executed in England,
mostly by the hideous method of burning at the
stake, a punishment which was reserved for
heresy at the time. The first executions
took place in February of 1555 and were largely
made up of Protestant leaders and clergy,
but following Mary’s false pregnancy and
humiliation later that year they accelerated.
Executions for heresy had occurred with some
general regularity during her father’s reign,
but the scale of them in the mid-1550s
was unprecedented. While they shocked
the English Protestant community, it should not
be assumed that Roman Catholics were appalled.
Most would have turned out to Smithfield
in London to watch the burnings convinced
that they were seeing the end of heretics who
deserved their fiery damnation. Mary’s decisions
in ordering the burnings were popular at the time,
as were most of her other religious policies.
Had she lived longer she would almost certainly
have returned England, where the population was
still largely Catholic, to the Roman Catholic fold
and stopped the spread of Protestantism there.
That she has been remembered instead as “Bloody
Mary” is in large part owing to the propagandists
of the subsequent reign of Elizabeth, and above
all one text, John Foxe’s Acts and Monuments,
more popularly known as Foxe’s Book of
Martyrs. Besides the Bible, this book
became for a time in the early modern era the
most widely-read book in the English language,
setting the seal on Mary’s historical
reputation as a zealot and a butcher.
In it the persecution of the Protestants killed
during Mary’s reign was described at length.
The illustrations which accompanied
the text depicted the burnings.
Probably the most famous Marian martyr documented
by Foxe was the former Archbishop of Canterbury,
Thomas Cranmer. Cranmer had been imprisoned
as soon as Mary ascended the throne. At trial
he had caved in and renounced his Protestantism.
Typically, it was the practice to spare the lives
of repentant heretics if they recanted their
previous beliefs in public. Mary, however,
was feeling vengeful when it came to Cranmer, a
figure who was central to her mother’s divorce
from Henry, and insisted that he would die. The
plan backfired. When Cranmer was paraded out on
the 21st of March 1556, he found his courage and
abandoned his plans to offer a further recantation
in the hope that he would be spared. Instead, in
a speech he disavowed his earlier recantation,
reaffirmed his Protestant faith and denounced
the Pope as the anti-Christ. He was then
roughly pulled down from the platform and taken to
the scaffold where he was committed to the flames.
Cranmer died what Foxe would later
describe as a magnificent martyr’s death.
As the flames were ignited before him, the former
archbishop thrust his right hand into the flames
to burn it first for the sin of signing
the recantation of his Protestant faith.
As Foxe recounted in the Book of Martyrs, his
last words were “Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.
I see the heavens open and Jesus standing
at the right hand of God.”
Eventually there was some turning of public
opinion against the execution of Cranmer and
the other Protestant martyrs. This, combined with
ongoing harvest failures, her false pregnancy
and her husband’s abandonment of her, tarnished
Mary’s image by 1557 and 1558. These issues
were compounded by war. In March of 1557, Philip,
who had succeeded his own father as King of Spain,
returned to England to convince Mary that England
should provide troops to support the Spanish in
their most recent war with the French. Initially
things went well, with a major joint Spanish and
English victory against the French at the Battle
of St. Quentin in northern France in August 1557.
But, things took a catastrophic turn in January
1558 when the French seized control of Calais,
the last English stronghold on the continent, and
the French port from which many English people
had assumed England would one day begin
to conquer parts of France yet again,
as they had in the glory days of King Edward III
and King Henry V during the Hundred Years’ War.
This loss was the final blow to Mary’s image
as Queen. Furthermore, the fact that the Pope
was allied with the King of France against
Philip strained England’s relationship with
Catholic Rome, impeding Mary’s goals of a
full return to the Roman Catholic fold.
Some months after Philip had returned to Spain
in July 1557, Mary believed that she was pregnant
once again. As the months wore on though,
Mary’s abdomen initially swelled, but then
her appetite disappeared as she grew thinner and
weaker. Most suspected that she was terribly ill
rather than pregnant. By the spring of 1558 many
were already preparing for the succession of her
half-sister Elizabeth. By the autumn, Mary began
preparing some last wishes. She endowed monastic
and educational institutions with bequests and
scholarships and instructed that daily masses
should be said for her soul and for those of
her parents. She also requested that her mother,
Catherine of Aragon, be exhumed from her grave
at Peterborough Cathedral, so that mother and
daughter might be buried together at Westminster
Abbey. This last request was never carried out.
Historians believe that it was ovarian or uterine
cancer that claimed Mary’s life on the 17th of
November 1558 at 42 years of age. She had probably
been living with it for years, as it would explain
her earlier phantom pregnancy. Mary was buried
in Westminster Abbey in a modest tomb, one which
would become much more elaborate when Elizabeth,
forty-five years later, was buried next to her.
Inscribed above their resting place, is a
Latin inscription which translated reads,
“Consorts in realm and tomb, we sisters,
Elizabeth and Mary, here lie down to sleep,
in hope of the resurrection.” One was
a Catholic, one was a Protestant.
There would be no repeat of the chaos of Lady Jane
Grey’s revolt in 1553 when Mary died in November
1558. A smooth succession occurred with Elizabeth,
the last of Henry VIII’s children from any of
his marriages, succeeding her half-sister. The
daughter of Anne Boleyn was a moderate Protestant,
one who liked the ostentation and trappings
of Roman Catholicism, but skewed doctrinally
towards Lutheranism. Thus, a moderate form of
Protestantism was re-imposed from 1558 onwards
and the Protestant exiles on the continent
began to make their way home to England.
Elizabeth’s reign lasted 45 years and it was
this longevity more so than anything else
which ensured the success of the Protestant
Reformation after decades of shifts back and forth
between Catholicism and Protestantism. By the time
Elizabeth died in 1603 a majority of English men
and women had been born after 1558 and had
grown up in the Anglican Protestant faith.
Mary’s efforts to restore England to the Catholic
fold were a failure as a result in the long run
and her reputation was systematically
torn apart by Foxe and others
through the books they published
from the late 1550s onwards.
Mary Tudor is generally deemed to have been one of
the most controversial of all England’s monarchs.
The legend of “Bloody Mary” is that England
was drifting benignly towards Protestantism
in the sixteenth century when she came
to the throne and inflicted a five-year
reign of terror on her subjects in her
quest to re-impose Roman Catholicism.
The reality is that England was still
broadly Roman Catholic in 1553 and Mary
simply engaged in a campaign to reverse what
were perceived by many English people at the time
as religious aberrations inflicted on England by
her father and in particular her half-brother.
It is also not as though she was alone in
doing this. While they occurred over a longer
time frame, over 200 heretics were killed in
England during the reign of her half-sister,
while revolts which had religious overtones during
the reigns of both Henry VIII and Edward VI,
such as the Pilgrimage of Grace in the 1530s and
Kett’s Rebellion in Norfolk in 1549, resulted
in hundreds of deaths. The Northern Rising of
1569 was a Roman Catholic revolt in the north of
England which was suppressed, following which at
least 700 Catholic insurrectionists were executed
through martial law by Elizabeth’s government.
If Mary was particularly bloody on account of her
religion, so too were her father, half-brother
and half-sister. That Mary has been remembered
in the fashion that she has been shows how
effectively John Foxe did his job in writing his
Book of Martyrs. Other than this, we might say
of Mary that she was a woman who had a very
difficult life owing to her father’s actions
in the late 1520s and throughout the 1530s,
continued to experience difficulties during
the reign of her Protestant half-brother,
and responded when she became queen by
doubling down on her own Catholic convictions,
initiating a campaign of repression against
the burgeoning Protestant church in England.
Ultimately, she was a typical monarch of Europe
during the brutality that was the Wars of Religion
unleashed by the Protestant Reformation.
What do you think of Queen Mary I?
Does she deserve her reputation as “Bloody
Mary”, the vicious burner of heretics,
or is her poor reputation simply a sign of the
success of subsequent Protestant propagandists
like John Foxe who unfairly condemned a
queen who was popular in her own time? Please
let us know in the comment section, and in the
meantime, thank you very much for watching!
The woman known to history as Queen
Elizabeth I of England and Ireland
was born on the 7th of September 1533
at Greenwich Palace near London.
Her father was King Henry VIII, the second son of
King Henry VII, who had ruled England between 1485
and 1509, having emerged victorious from the
series of civil wars which wracked England
in the fifteenth century known as the Wars of
the Roses. Elizabeth’s mother was Anne Boleyn,
the second wife of Henry VIII and briefly the
Queen Consort of England between 1533 and 1536.
The circumstances of Elizabeth’s birth would
dictate the first quarter of a century of
her life. Her parents had hoped for a son
to provide Henry VIII with a long-desired
legitimate male heir to continue the Tudor line
and prevent any fall back into the civil wars
which had characterized English
politics in the fifteenth century. Thus,
while Elizabeth’s birth was celebrated, and she
was promptly proclaimed Henry’s heir presumptive,
jumping past her half-sister Mary, born of
Henry’s first marriage to Catherine of Aragon,
there was no denying that Henry and Anne
were disappointed not to have had a boy.
This desire for a male heir had characterized
Henry VIII’s reign since the mid-1520s and had
resulted in his long-running quest for a legal
divorce from his first wife between 1527 and 1533.
Nevertheless, when a daughter arrived in
1533 the king and queen made the best of it
and claimed that a boy would soon
follow. Meanwhile, in December 1533,
the three-month-old Princess Elizabeth was
established in her own royal household at
Hatfield, staffed by numerous servants and a
group of guardians handpicked by her mother.
Most of Elizabeth’s closest attendants
were extended Boleyn relatives.
Though she was only a baby, Elizabeth was a
chess piece in the English politics of the 1530s.
Before long her father’s patience with her mother
began to wear thin, as Anne suffered multiple
miscarriages in the mid-1530s and the son she
had promised the king never arrived. In May 1536,
after a series of outlandish claims, including
the suggestion that Anne had been in an incestuous
relationship with her own brother, emerged, Anne
was executed for charges of adultery, incest, and
treason. The charges were probably fabricated as
a means for Henry to dispense of his second wife.
Not long thereafter the Boleyn marriage was
annulled on the basis that Henry had been
seduced into it by some form of withcraft.
This rendered Elizabeth illegitimate and
within two weeks of Anne’s death Henry was
married to his third wife, Jane Seymour.
He soon ceased supporting Elizabeth’s household
in the fashion that he previously had.
Then, in July of 1536, the English parliament
passed the Succession Act, which stated that
Henry’s marriage to Anne Boleyn had been invalid,
officially rendering Elizabeth illegitimate.
Henry had always demonstrated an attachment to
his eldest daughter, Mary, born in 1516 from his
marriage to Catherine of Aragon, and he had been
quick to welcome her back into the fold in the
1530s once she agreed to end her obstinate refusal
to acknowledge Henry’s divorce of her mother.
The king did not immediately make such an effort
for his younger daughter and continued to keep her
at arm’s length in the years following her
mother’s execution. Indeed, Elizabeth’s governess,
Lady Margaret Bryan, was soon writing to
Thomas Cromwell, Henry’s chief minister,
begging him to intercede with the King
on the child’s behalf. In her letter,
Lady Bryan wrote that Elizabeth was growing out
of her clothes quickly and there were insufficient
resources to keep her in a manner befitting a
daughter of the king, legitimate or illegitimate.
Such were the financial straits at Hatfield
that two members of Elizabeth’s household
were even charged for poaching deer in
the parklands surrounding the house.
The birth in October 1537 of Prince
Edward, Henry’s first legitimate male heir,
changed matters, though it resulted in
the death two weeks later of Jane Seymour,
Henry’s third wife, owing to post-natal
complications. With a male heir now in place,
Elizabeth and Mary were re-integrated
back into the Henrician court more fully,
their positions as either legitimate or
illegitimate being somewhat nullified when there
was now a male successor to the throne. Moreover,
before her death and while she was pregnant,
Jane had encouraged the king to restore Elizabeth
to a better position. The belated manner in which
Henry accepted Elizabeth into the royal household
contrasted sharply with her character. Of all his
children, Elizabeth would prove to be the most
like her father. She resembled Henry, with the
same light, reddish hair, pale skin, and ruddy
cheeks, though with her mother Anne’s brown eyes.
She would also prove herself in years to come to
have the same hard-headedness of her father.
Elizabeth received a very good education in the
late 1530s and throughout the 1540s and soon
proved to be one of the most brilliantly learned
women in sixteenth-century Europe. She spoke five
languages, English, French, Spanish, Italian and
Latin, and could read Greek and Dutch to some
extent. When an Irish aristocrat visiting court
many years later wanted to gain her attention,
he presented her with a small dictionary of key
phrases in the Irish language. Her scholarly work
involved translating ancient Latin text such
as Boethius’ The Consolation of Philosophy
and Tacitus’ Annals. As she was being educated in
the 1540s she grew closer to her younger brother,
Prince Edward, who was much closer in age
to her than was Mary. Elizabeth carried the
chrisom at Edward’s baptism, they shared some
of the same tutors in the years that followed,
and they were both influenced by the same ardently
Protestant reformers at the Henrician court.
During her early years, Elizabeth found
surrogate mothers in her governesses
and in a succession of stepmothers. The
Protestant German princess, Anne of Cleves,
whom Henry married when Elizabeth was six
years old, took an interest in Henry’s
youngest daughter. Her marriage to Henry lasted
only a few months before he acquired an annulment,
but Anne and Elizabeth continued to visit and
write to each other following the divorce.
She did not develop a close relationship with her
father’s fifth wife, Catherine Howard, a niece of
the Duke of Norfolk who wed Henry when she was 17
years old in 1540. She was dead not much over a
year and a half later after committing adultery
with a courtier by the name of Thomas Culpeper.
When this latest stepmother was executed,
Elizabeth drew an important lesson from it.
The princess, no doubt remembering what had
happened to her mother as well, remarked to
her childhood friend, Robert Dudley, “I shall
never marry.” This lesson would be reinforced
over and over again as Elizabeth grew up and she
observed that married women were invariably at
the mercy of their husbands, surrendering
power and self-determination to them.
Henry’s sixth wife, Catherine Parr, whom Henry
married when Elizabeth was nine years old,
was also kind and motherly towards her. Catherine,
who authored several books herself, recognized
the young princess’ intellectual potential
and encouraged her in her academic pursuits.
Catherine is also usually credited with persuading
Henry to restore both Mary and Elizabeth to the
line of succession to the throne, after their
younger brother Edward. Beyond these stepmothers,
it was the serving members of Elizabeth’s
household, most of whom were extended relations
of her mother, Anne Boleyn, with whom Elizabeth
developed the closest relationships, particularly
her beloved governess, Catherine “Cat” Ashley,
who would remain with Elizabeth as lady-in-waiting
when she became queen many years later, while
William Cecil, a rising official esteemed for his
intelligence and abilities, served in his younger
years as the surveyor of Elizabeth’s household.
Elizabeth was thirteen years old
when her father died in January 1547.
It must have been a difficult event full of
conflicting emotions for a girl who by then
was old enough to know that her father had
sanctioned the execution of her mother.
Henry was generous to his daughters in his will,
allowing each of them an annual income of £3,000.
With Henry’s death, nine-year-old Edward became
King Edward VI. A regency council was appointed to
govern for him during his childhood years. This
was first headed by his uncle Edward Seymour,
who became Lord Protector of England and the Duke
of Somerset. The Dowager Queen, Catherine Parr,
invited Elizabeth to live with her
and her new husband, Thomas Seymour,
Somerset’s brother, whom Catherine had
married within months of the king’s death,
something which many people disapproved of.
Elizabeth’s experiences here were less than ideal.
Thomas Seymour was an unscrupulous man,
constantly in pursuit of greater power.
Clearly his marriage to Catherine had not fully
satisfied his ambitions and he began to engage in
highly inappropriate behaviour towards Elizabeth
once she was ensconced in their household.
He frequently visited her bedchamber in
the early mornings, still in his nightgown,
sitting on her bed uninvited and tickling her.
Elizabeth began to get up earlier in the mornings,
ensuring that her maids attended her as
early as possible to avoid Seymour’s visits.
It must have been enormously confusing
to her when her stepmother, rather than
confront her husband about his behavior, began
to participate in the peculiar horseplay.
This leaves us with many questions and, if true,
it is a damning indictment of both Seymour and
Parr. Did Catherine believe that her husband’s
behavior towards her stepdaughter was in fact
innocent and all in fun? Was she jealous or
insecure and seeking to keep herself involved
in her husband’s activities? Whatever
Catherine’s beliefs and motives were,
she promptly sent Elizabeth away in May 1548,
when she unexpectedly discovered her husband
and fifteen-year-old stepdaughter, quote: “in an
embrace.” To give Catherine the benefit of the
doubt, she may very well have sent Elizabeth away
to protect her, while she was seemingly unable to
control her husband’s behaviour. After being sent
away, Elizabeth never saw her stepmother again.
The two exchanged a few letters
after Elizabeth’s departure, but
Catherine Parr died as a result of complications
from childbirth less than four months later.
Unfortunately, Elizabeth had not heard the
last of Thomas Seymour. With Catherine dead,
he began actively pursuing Elizabeth’s hand
in marriage. It is difficult to determine how
Elizabeth felt about this. Seymour was around 40
years old at the time, whereas she was fifteen,
but such age differences were not entirely unusual
in early modern times when it came to organising
political marriages. And a marriage between
one of the king’s uncles and his half-sister
would most certainly be a political match
were it to occur. What foiled Seymour’s plan
was that he acted in secret and when details
of what he was conspiring towards became public
it had the look of a political conspiracy by
him. When it was revealed, the Privy Council
had him detained and questioned. Elizabeth was
interrogated closely about the Seymour plot,
but she adamantly denied any involvement on her
part in any plans or schemes of which King Edward
or the Privy Council did not approve,
including any question of marriage.
The Seymour episode eventually blew over.
Elizabeth likely learned a great deal from it.
For the next two years she passed most of her
time at Hatfield, immersed in her studies, and
wrote regularly and dutifully to her brother, King
Edward. She began to visit court more regularly,
beginning in or around 1551. There she became the
very model of the virtuous princess, dressing with
modesty and little ostentation. Elizabeth was
Protestant in her religious leanings, though
she was much more moderate than her brother the
king. Edward was emerging as a Calvinist monarch
and had overseen the adoption of a radical form of
Protestantism in the late 1540s and early 1550s.
Elizabeth, conversely, favoured some
doctrinal elements of Protestantism
but still admired the pomp and ceremony of
Roman Catholicism. As with so much else,
she was much like her father in that
regard. In the early summer of 1553,
with Edward profoundly ill, Elizabeth was warned
by William Cecil that the king was dying and that
there was a plot afoot to imprison both herself
and her half-sister Mary and place Lady Jane Grey,
a great-granddaughter of Henry VII, on the throne
as a Protestant stooge controlled by the Duke of
Northumberland, who had emerged as the foremost
figure in Edward’s government in the early 1550s.
When Edward VI died on the 6th of
July 1553, possibly from tuberculosis,
Lady Jane Grey was proclaimed Queen. Athough
Elizabeth mourned her brother’s passing,
Edward’s attempt to defy their father’s will
and remove both Mary and Elizabeth from the
line of succession rankled her. Thus, when
the Privy Council proclaimed Mary as queen,
in defiance of Northumberland’s efforts to make
Lady Jane Grey queen, Elizabeth promptly wrote to
Mary to signal her support for her cause, despite
Mary’s well-known zealous Roman Catholicism.
Elizabeth accompanied the new queen as
she progressed triumphantly into London
in August of 1553, the Grey cause
having collapsed almost immediately.
Mary’s reign would prove tumultuous for
Elizabeth. As a Protestant and Mary’s heir,
she was a figurehead for those English people
who would rather see a Protestant on the throne.
Accordingly, even in instances where she did
not encourage it, she was made a figurehead of
opposition to the Marian regime, most dangerously
in the case of the rebellion in early 1554
of Thomas Wyatt, an insurrection which Elizabeth
had nothing to do with but nevertheless
led to her being detained in the Tower of London
for some time. Throughout these unsettling years
Elizabeth could never be certain that her
life was secure and she cleaved ever closer
to the serving members of her household, whom she
considered her family. These included the Ashleys,
the Sheltons and William Cecil. She also
grew closer during these years to her friend,
Robert Dudley, whom she referred to affectionately
as “sweet Robin.” Robert was a son of John Dudley,
Duke of Northumberland, whom Queen Mary had
executed for his part in the plot to raise Lady
Jane Grey to the throne. The apparent closeness
between the princess and Dudley was controversial.
He had been married since
1550 to Amy Robsart.
In April of 1555, Elizabeth’s house arrest
abruptly ended, when Queen Mary summoned her
to court. The queen was labouring under the belief
that she was expecting a child and requested that
Elizabeth join her in her confinement. Elizabeth
dutifully attended her sister in the birthing
chamber throughout the summer, but Mary’s due date
came and went and no baby was born. It had been a
phantom pregnancy and Elizabeth remained the heir
to the throne. In the aftermath of this incident,
Mary invited Elizabeth to remain at court,
giving her chambers befitting her position,
and allowing her more and more freedom as
time went on. It is possible that Mary’s
conduct in this matter indicated some renewal of
sisterly feeling between the two women. However,
Mary may also have invited Elizabeth to remain
at court simply to keep a closer eye on her.
Elizabeth remained at Hatfield for the next two
years. During this time, she and Robert Dudley
became closer than ever. He visited her often and
they enjoyed many of the same pursuits, including
riding, hunting, dancing, playing at cards,
and witty conversation. Elizabeth and Robert
seemed not to care about the implications of
their relationship when in each other’s company,
and there was little Elizabeth’s advisors such
as William Cecil could say to dissuade her.
Elizabeth endured two years of tension and
uncertainty after her return to Hatfield.
Then matters changed very dramatically. On the
17th of November 1558, her sister Mary died,
most likely of ovarian or uterine cancer, a likely
explanation for some of the symptoms accompanying
her phantom pregnancies. Lacking any other heir,
Elizabeth, the last of the children of Henry VIII,
was promptly proclaimed as Queen Elizabeth I
of England. It was not immediately apparent
whether Elizabeth intended to rule as
a Protestant or a Catholic monarch.
For her part, Elizabeth was content that this
ambiguity should last as long as possible,
until she could consolidate her power and
establish a government. She well understood
that England was still heavily Catholic, as
were many of the nobles and clergy around her.
Nearly two decades of separation from Rome had
rendered many English ambivalent about Papal
supremacy, even those who considered
themselves to be loyal Catholics.
The English parliament thus proved willing to
grant Elizabeth the title of “Supreme Governor
of the Church of England” without really knowing
what the queen’s wider religious stance was.
The Elizabethan religious settlement would only
unfold in the course of 1559 and 1560.
Elizabeth understood that she had to proceed
carefully while her reign was still new and
uncertain. Queen Mary’s body lay in state
at St. James’ Palace until mid-December,
with regular Catholic vigils performed
until her interrment at Westminster.
Elizabeth continued to have the Latin mass
celebrated in her private chapel, but demonstrated
her discomfort with Catholicism in other small
ways, such as requesting removal of specifically
Catholic rituals such as the raising of the host
during mass. Elizabeth ensured that her sister’s
funeral was both magnificent and in keeping with
Catholic tradition, although she did imprison
a eulogizing priest following it for vaguely
referring to her supposed illegitimacy.
On the day of her coronation, the 15th of January
1559, Elizabeth processed through the city of
London as the people cheered her joyfully. She was
anointed and crowned Queen of England and Ireland
in Westminster Abbey, entering the church
dressed in magnificent royal robes of gold,
trimmed with ermine and jewels, her long red
hair loose and flowing. As Elizabeth passed by,
attendees promptly cut off pieces of the blue
carpet upon which she walked as souvenirs.
Ever conscious of how controversial her Protestant
faith still was to many of her subjects,
Elizabeth’s coronation was a largely Catholic
service. Even within a largely Catholic ceremony,
Elizabeth did not prostrate herself for
the anointing. Instead she simply knelt
in a dignified fashion. Moreover, as soon as the
Latin mass began, the Queen promptly withdrew to
a private chamber to change her costume
for the upcoming feast and celebration.
This was clearly designed as a public statement
of her rejection of some of the Catholic rites,
carefully choreographed to indicate to the
political nation that further religious changes
would come in the months ahead. Emerging in
an exquisite costume of purple and ermine,
she headed the procession out of the church,
smiling and graciously greeting members of the
cheering crowds. Elizabeth had cleverly
managed to have herself crowned in a way
which seemed to placate both Catholics
and Protestants to varying extents.
One of Elizabeth’s first acts as Queen was what
is known as the Elizabethan Religious Settlement.
At her first official parliament, she had
her government pass an Act of Uniformity,
which reinstated the 1549 Book of Common Prayer
that had been a bedrock of her half-brother’s
Protestant settlement, although
a few alterations were introduced into it in line
with Elizabeth’s much more moderate Protestantism.
One sticking point concerned the real presence
of Christ’s body and blood in the Eucharist,
known as transubstantiation, which Catholics
believed in and Protestants did not.
Some historians argue that the liturgical
alterations of the Elizabethan era made
it possible for both Protestants and Catholics to
interpret communion as they pleased. In addition,
because Elizabeth was fond of the ceremony
and pageantry of the Roman Catholic Church,
the traditional Catholic vestments worn
by priests and clerics were preserved
under the new Elizabethan Religious Settlement,
as were the images and crucifixes in churches
and monasteries across England. This would become
a major point of contention for more hardline
Protestant reformers in England, who believed
ostentation of this kind was idolatrous. Elizabeth
also filled as many bishoprics and archbishoprics
as possible with Protestant clerics,
removing Catholic bishops appointed by Mary in
the process. All in all, Elizabeth imposed a very
moderate form of Lutheran Protestantism in the
late 1550s and early 1560s, but it would never
please a large cohort of radical Calvinists
in England who became known as the Puritans
and who wanted a form of Protestantism based
largely on the theocracy Jean Calvin had created
in the city of Geneva in the Swiss Confederacy
back in the 1530s and 1540s. Clashes between
the government and the Puritans would remain
a constant feature of Elizabeth’s long reign.
This disagreement illustrates the level
of religious discord which was prevalent,
not just in England, but across
Europe during the sixteenth century,
Elizabeth’s religious settlement decreed
punishment for refusal to attend Sunday services
or for other examples of Catholic failure to
conform, but the penalties were small fines,
which frequently went unenforced, depending
on religious sympathies in a given region.
Many Catholic clergy and the laity found
it convenient to conform outwardly,
while inwardly retaining their own beliefs.
Indeed, as Elizabeth once wisely declared,
quote: “There is only one Christ, one
faith, all else is a dispute over trifles.”
The English certainly had their religious
struggles, but under Elizabeth these struggles
were considerably less violent than they proved
to be elsewhere in Europe, such as in France
where the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre of
1572 would see Parisian Catholics massacre
over 3,000 Protestant Huguenots in a single
day. This was in the midst of forty years of
religious wars in France between the 1560s and the
1590s. Compared to this level of religious strife,
England remained calm under Elizabeth, and more
than a decade would pass after her accession to
the throne before the religious question erupted
into any form of major violence in England.
England’s administrative, economic and military
infrastructure all needed urgent attention.
Henry VIII had spent ruinously during
his reign and neither Edward nor Mary
had ruled for long enough to fully correct the
problems he bequeathed to them. Conversely,
wars during both Elizabeth’s half-sibling’s reigns
and harvest failures had compounded the problem.
English trade had declined as well, following
the decreasing value of the English currency.
Elizabeth worked closely with her newly
appointed Secretary of State, William Cecil, the
de-facto head of her government for the next forty
years, and Thomas Gresham, financier, merchant
and longtime economic advisor to the Tudors,
to formulate a strategy to rescue the economy.
By 1561 all of the debased currency had been
withdrawn from circulation, dissolved and replaced
with freshly minted coins of gold and silver
that re-established confidence in the face value
of the English coinage. The recovery of England’s
currency helped the economy rebound nicely.
Prices stabilized and trade boomed once more. In
addition, Gresham founded London’s Royal Exchange
early in the reign, after being inspired by his
direct experiences of the Antwerp Bourse where
English cloth merchants had been carrying out much
of their trade in the Low Countries for decades.
An island nation requires ships, for both economic
and military purposes. Elizabeth understood that
a good deal of investment was needed in this
area, yet, she was still constrained by budgets.
Therefore the process of naval expansion was
a careful and practical one during her reign.
The ships built during Elizabeth’s reign
tended to be multi-purpose in design,
meant for trade, exploration, fishing
and warfare. They were smaller,
faster and more maneuverable than the standard
warship, and yet not so diminutive that they could
not be equipped with multiple gun carriages.
Several dozen were built for the royal fleet
and they were so in a semi-private manner whereby
nobles and mariners offset some of the cost by
having semi-control over the ships when they were
built. Ships, of course, require experienced and
competent men to man them and Elizabeth and Cecil
patronised a number of highly skilled mariners
from the English West Country, men like Humphrey
Gilbert, Martin Frobisher and Walter Raleigh,
as well as sailors from ports like Bristol who
had decades of experience leading expeditions
to the valuable fisheries off the “Grand
Banks” of Newfoundland in North America.
Their exploration of the North American seaboard
was an important, though often under-appreciated,
precursor to the English colonisation of
North America in the seventeenth century.
England’s economic recovery was impressive,
and much credit is due to Elizabeth and her
advisors for overseeing it, especially
since regular taxation was not a strategy
England could resort to, as taxes had to
be approved by parliament. Instead a large
source of funding for England’s recovery came
from crown land revenues and customs duties.
Due to this, Elizabeth’s court was markedly
less extravagant than her father’s.
She kept her staff and that of the Privy
Council, the main governing body of the realm,
small, installing most of the members of her
traditional household in positions at court.
Entertainments and banquets in the early years
were elegant, but not overly extravagant.
Indeed, such was the manner in which Elizabeth
was determined to put the state’s finances
on a better footing than had been seen since
the days of her grandfather, King Henry VII,
that she became notorious for her parsimony and
unwillingness to spend excessive amounts of money
on grand projects. In the long run this
was a judicious policy for the most part
and despite its limited resources the English
government accomplished quite a lot during the
Elizabethan era. However, it frequently infuriated
her councillors, who viewed the Queen as a ruler
who constantly changed her mind on policy matters,
often based on her concerns about expenditure.
There was one particular area where
Elizabeth could not avoid spending money.
This was in Ireland. When she came to the throne
in 1558, Elizabeth also became Queen of Ireland,
yet the island remained only partially under
English control. Dozens of largely independent
Irish lords ruled different parts of the
country, whereas English rule was largely
confined to Dublin and the Pale which surrounded
it in Leinster. A programme of regional conquest
and colonisation had been entered into towards
the end of her father’s reign and would play out
for decades during Elizabeth’s reign. Initially,
the weaknesses of Elizabeth’s government were
plain for all to see, as Shane O’Neill, the head
of the foremost Irish lordship in the country,
the O’Neills of Ulster, raided the Pale
on numerous occasions in the early 1560s.
He was only finally defeated in 1567 because he
overextended himself in the north of the country
and was killed by his erstwhile allies,
the MacDonnells of western Scotland.
Further wars and plantations occurred consistently
through the 1570s and 1580s, gradually
reducing the Irish lords, though at a large cost
to Elizabeth’s exchequer, much to her dismay.
Because Elizabeth was young, unmarried and
childless, the question of her marriage was
intensely debated all throughout the 1560s and
1570s. England needed an heir. Unlike Edward and
Mary before her, there was no sibling waiting to
step into the breach and succeed her if Elizabeth
died. Furthermore, the closest remaining
heir to the English throne was Mary Stuart,
Queen of Scots, a granddaughter of Margaret
Tudor, Henry VIII’s sister. Mary was a Catholic
and so Elizabeth and her advisors understood
that the preservation of the new Protestant
religious settlement in England depended on Mary
Queen of Scots never securing the English throne,
even though she had the best claim in law to it
if Elizabeth died childless. Therefore, as soon
as the reign commenced, the issue of Elizabeth’s
marriage arose and suitors began to appear.
However, much to the great consternation of
her advisors and the political realm at large,
Elizabeth seemed to only appear to be
interested in Robert Dudley, who she
appointed as Master of the Horse and made the
Earl of Leicester several years into the reign.
Tongues wagged throughout the late 1550s and
early 1560s about Dudley’s excessive influence
and the nature of his relationship with the
queen. This was compounded in September 1560
when Robert’s wife, Amy Robsart, died
suddenly under suspicious circumstances.
Amy was found at the bottom of a staircase
with her neck broken, following which theories
of foul play abounded, with many presuming
Dudley had thrown his wife down the stairs,
breaking her neck in the process, in order to
free himself up to marry the Queen. The theory
is generally discounted by most historians today
and Amy’s death was most likely an accident.
The reality is that it was always unlikely
that Elizabeth would marry Dudley.
He was an English lord and by the second half
of the sixteenth century it was an accepted norm
that a monarch like Elizabeth would marry
a member of another European royal family,
the better to cement an alliance of some
kind. Yet Elizabeth did none of these things.
Already in the 1560s she was cultivating the
public image of herself as The Virgin Queen,
pledged in marriage to the realm, rather than
a husband, and mother to all of her people.
This campaign manifested itself in Elizabeth’s
speeches, in the portraiture she commissioned,
and it even appeared in the poems and plays of
the time. Elizabeth would continue to entertain
suitors for her hand, most notably King Eric XIV
of Sweden and Francis, Duke of Alencon and Anjou,
brother of King Henry III of France,
but she ultimately refused them all.
She would remain unmarried her entire life.
It is hard to escape the fact that there was
a complicated psychology at work here, Elizabeth
having grown up at the Henrician court where her
father married and then dispensed with one wife
after another, Elizabeth’s own mother included.
She eventually determined not to subjugate herself
to a husband in this way, though her court became
a peculiar place where a succession of favourites
including Dudley, Sir Christopher Hatton,
Sir Walter Raleigh and later the second Earl
of Essex gained her favour by courting her
as one would a prospective bride, all the while
knowing that no marriage would ever follow.
In 1562, Elizabeth, who was in her late
twenties by then, contracted smallpox.
She recovered without significant
long-term damage to her overall health, but
the disease left her face badly scarred, a common
occurrence amongst those who contracted smallpox
in early modern times. In order to disguise
the scars she began to wear elaborate makeup.
Unfortunately, the white make-up she wore to mask
her scarred complexion every day was lead-based,
and the vermillion she used to redden her cheeks
and lips contained significant amounts of mercury.
The regular use of these compounds damaged her
skin and possibly contributed to her hair loss
in later years. As this compounded the
problem caused by the smallpox scars,
Elizabeth caked herself in more layers of makeup
and took to wearing elaborate wigs in later life.
Finally, her teeth began to blacken
and decay due to her sweet tooth.
Sugar was a novelty in Europe, one
introduced from the Americas. All of this
would leave her in later life a woman with ravaged
skin, extensive hair loss and rotted teeth.
Amongst the achievements of the Elizabethan
period, one which deserves attention
is that this was an early golden age of English
literature. Some of the greatest writers, poets,
and dramatists in English history worked at
this time and were patronised by the queen
and her courtiers. These included the playwrights,
Christopher Marlowe, William Shakespeare
and Ben Jonson, and the poets Edmund Spenser and
Philip Sidney. Walter Raleigh too was a poet,
though he is usually more well-known for
his explorations in the Americas. The sheer
breadth of Raleigh’s experiences encapsulate the
excitements and pursuits of the Elizabethan age.
He explored North America, founded the first,
albeit short-lived, English colonial settlement
in North America, at Roanoke Island, captured
Spanish gold as a privateer, and is sometimes
fantastically credited with introducing
tobacco to England and the potato to Ireland.
The exciting new frontiers of exploration and
trade broadened English horizons immensely,
just as the literary flowering did
for English culture. For instance,
between 1576 and 1578, Martin Frobisher
sailed in search of a Northwest Passage,
while Sir Francis Drake became only the second
person to ever circumnavigate the globe in 1581.
The first permanent colonies were not finally
settled by England in North America until the
early seventeenth century, but much of the
groundwork in terms of exploration and mapping
was completed during Elizabeth’s reign. A
major drive in all of this was a desire to
strike in an indirect fashion at Spain, the
pre-eminent colonial power in the Americas,
by attacking Spanish shipping in the Atlantic
and trying to present a threat in North America.
The first years of Elizabeth’s reign had seen
fairly good relations between England and Spain,
King Philip II of Spain having only recently been
King of England through his marriage to Queen
Mary. But relations gradually soured in the course
of the 1560s as Elizabeth refused Spanish offers
for her to marry Philip, while her religious
settlement also put England at loggerheads with
Catholic Spain. Finally, there were a number of
diplomatic clashes over shipping in the Atlantic.
By the 1570s, England and Spain were
involved in a sort of unofficial cold war,
but it would take until the second half
of the 1580s before open war commenced.
All of this was tied up with an ongoing succession
crisis, in which the religion of Elizabeth’s most
likely heir, Mary Queen of Scots, was the
main issue. Elizabeth refused to acknowledge
the Catholic Mary as her potential successor
in the 1560s and 1570s. The Queen of Scots
was a Catholic, and for Elizabeth to encourage
her claim would be to open herself up to the
plots and determination of Catholics to place
one of their own on the throne of England,
and so restore Catholicism, Elizabeth hoped
to contain Mary’s ambitions through diplomacy,
but this proved to be impossible. Mary had lived
out her youth in France with her mother’s family,
but she returned to Scotland in 1561 to
take up her rightful position as queen.
Mary’s presence in Scotland would prove
inflammatory. Her Catholicism aroused the
animosity of the Scottish Protestant Lords of
the Congregation, who in 1560 had established
a form of Calvinist Protestantism in Scotland as
the state religion. Mary was soon a major source
of contention in Scotland and for years to come
in the 1560s conspiracies surrounded her.
As with Elizabeth to the south in England, there
was a major debate surrounding Mary’s potential
marriage. At one time rumours had abounded that
Dudley would head north to Scotland and marry
Mary, but instead she wed Henry Stuart, Lord
Darnley, in 1565. Darnley and Mary were cousins
and were both grandchildren of
Margaret Tudor, Henry VIII’s sister.
They were also both Catholics. As such, this
marriage posed an enormous threat to Elizabeth
and the Protestant settlement in England,
particularly so once Mary have birth to a son,
the future King James VI of Scotland, in the
summer of 1566. It was assumed that he would be
raised as a Catholic in keeping with his mother’s
religion. There then followed an extraordinary
series of events in which Mary began an affair
with James Hepburn, the earl of Bothwell,
who was then accused of murdering Darnley in
the spring of 1567. Mary married Bothwell within
weeks of Darnley’s suspicious death and then was
imprisoned not long after by the Scottish lords,
who were appalled at her conduct. She was then
forced to abdicate in favour of her infant son,
James, who succeeded as King James VI
of Scotland at just one year of age.
He would now be raised by some of the seniormost
Scottish lords in the Protestant faith.
These developments might by themselves have
not been such a bad thing for Elizabeth and
the English government had matters
remained there. But within months
Mary had escaped from her imprisonment at
Lochleven Castle and, after an abortive
attempt at reclaiming the Scottish throne,
absconded over the border into northern England.
This placed Elizabeth and her ministers in London
in a very difficult position. Mary could not be
sent back to Scotland. To do so would potentially
lead to her execution by the Scottish lords and
Elizabeth was unwilling to send a fellow queen
to that fate. At the same time, her presence as
a Catholic contender to the English throne on
English soil made her a focus of conspiracies
by Roman Catholics in England and abroad. In
Rome, English Catholic exiles openly discussed
the possibility of launching a revolt in England
against Elizabeth’s government and then placing
Mary on the English throne as a means to restore
England yet again to the Catholic fold.
This was not idle speculation. In 1569 a major
revolt was initiated by some of the leading
Catholic lords of the north of England. Although
she was not directly involved in plotting this,
Mary’s position was important in the Northern
Rebellion. Though it was quickly crushed
and Elizabeth ordered the execution of some 750
Catholic rebels, it highlighted the precarious
situation with Mary present on English soil,
doubly so when Pope Pius V issued a Papal Bull,
Regnans in Excelsis in 1570 in response to
the suppression of the Northern Rebellion,
through which Elizabeth was excommunicated and
all true Catholics were enjoined to overthrow her.
This volatile situation would prevail for
nearly twenty years. Though Elizabeth never
met Mary in person, the deposed Scottish queen
would spend the entirety of the late 1560s,
the 1570s and much of the 1580s under house arrest
in a series of different palatial houses across
northern England. Many of Elizabeth’s senior
ministers such as Cecil would doubtlessly have
been delighted to have an opportunity to simply
have Mary killed and the threat she posed removed,
but Elizabeth simply refused to do
this to a fellow female monarch.
Again, there was a complex psychology to this and
we should remember that Elizabeth’s mother Anne
was a queen who had been executed three decades
before Mary arrived to northern England.
In the complex situation which developed with Mary
Queen of Scots over the next decade and a half,
Sir Francis Walsingham, the English Secretary
of State and chief spymaster from 1573 onwards,
was paramount. A committed Protestant,
Walsingham viewed himself as a religious warrior
whose work was to defend the Protestant settlement
in England from the threat Mary and others,
such as radical members of the English
Catholic exile community in Rome, posed.
He had personally witnessed the mass slaughter of
Protestants at the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre
in Paris while he was serving as England’s
ambassador there and he was determined
not to see the same thing happen in his
own country. Many plots by Catholics in
England and abroad were rooted out and crushed by
Walsingham and his spies in the 1570s and 1580s.
Then, finally, in 1586 he was presented with an
opportunity to end the greatest threat of all.
That year Walsingham became aware of a plot
centred on Anthony Babington, an English Catholic,
to assassinate Elizabeth and free Mary
before placing her on the throne of England.
Walsingham knew what was going on from very early
on in affairs, but rather than reveal it quickly
he placed double agents within Babington’s circle
and allowed him not only to incriminate himself
but Mary as well. When he finally revealed the
Babington Plot, not even Elizabeth could ignore
Mary’s treachery. She was placed on trial, found
guilty of treason and executed at Fotheringay
Castle on the 8th of February 1587. Elizabeth
had finally been coerced into signing Mary’s
death warrant after nearly two decades of keeping
her imprisoned in northern England. Yet she had
nearly faltered at the last, attempting to rescind
the order after she had given it. In the end
it was only because Walsingham, Cecil and other
members of the Privy Council had acted speedily
after she signed Mary’s death warrant that the
order was carried out, the councillors being aware
that Elizabeth would probably change her mind on
reflection. Killing a fellow queen was one of the
hardest decisions Elizabeth ever made, regardless
of how much of a threat Mary had posed.
The drama surrounding Mary’s presence in
England for so many years was connected
to the wider international situation in the
1570s and 1580s. When it came to foreign policy,
Elizabeth had always sought to
avoid an expensive outright war.
Her discreet encouragement of privateering and
the frequent attacks on Spanish bullion ships by
figures like Francis Drake were a cost-effective
way of waging an unofficial cold war with Spain,
as was providing financial and material support
to the Dutch rebels who were engaged in a war of
independence against Spain in the Netherlands
from 1568 onwards. She would doubtlessly
have continued in this vein had it not been for
events in France where the Wars of Religion,
a series of civil wars between Catholics,
Protestants and a politique faction that steered
a middle way between the two, had been underway
since the 1560s. In the 1580s, Philip II of Spain
was beginning to intervene there on the side
of the French Catholic League, while his armies
had also made advances in the Netherlands against
the Dutch. Faced with the possibility of the Dutch
revolt being crushed and France falling into
the Spanish camp, Elizabeth and her councillors
determined that they had no other option but to
risk an outright war with Spain. In August 1585
they agreed the Treaty of Nonsuch with the Dutch
and Elizabeth’s old love, Robert Dudley, the Earl
of Leicester, headed for the continent with an
English expeditionary force to aid the Dutch
in the Netherlands. The First Anglo-Spanish War
had commenced after years of shadow fighting.
Elizabeth expected Leicester to aid the Dutch
and to keep their rebellion alive, but without
committing too many English resources. However,
he immediately scuppered this by accepting the
position of Governor-General of the Netherlands
from the Dutch States General, something which
committed Elizabeth to defending the Dutch against
Spanish and Catholic aggression indefinitely.
She penned a sharp rebuke and ordered that it
be read in Dudley’s presence before the States
General, but the damage was done by then.
With the signing of the Treaty of Nonsuch,
Leicester’s subsequent actions in the Low
Countries and the execution of Mary Queen of
Scots early in 1587, the Spanish began preparing
an armada to try and invade and conquer England,
the ultimate goal being to depose Elizabeth
and return the country to the Catholic fold.
In anticipation of this, Elizabeth authorized
Drake to lead an expedition to the Spanish port of
Cadiz and attack the Spanish fleet that was being
prepared there before it could ever leave Spain.
The raid was a great success, with dozens of ships
destroyed, but it only stalled Philip II’s plans
for a time. By the spring of 1588 the lost ships
had been replaced and on the 12th of July 1588,
a Spanish armada of approximately 130 ships set
sail for the English Channel. The plan was for the
armada to sail through the Channel, pick up the
Spanish armies in the Netherlands and then convey
an army of tens of thousands of Spanish troops
to southern England. Against this Spanish Armada,
the English had hundreds of ships, but
most of these were small merchant ships
and the vessels of privateers, not the kind of
warships that comprised the Spanish fleet.
The odds seemed to be against an English victory
and on land an army was being prepared for if
the Spanish successfully made landfall.
The goal, of course, was to try and ever
prevent the armada from making contact with
the Spanish land forces in the Netherlands or
landing in England thereafter. The conclusive sea
battle took place over approximately two weeks.
On the 19th of July 1588, the Spanish
fleet was first sighted off Plymouth.
The next day, the English sailed out to fire on
the Spanish. The English ships proved much faster
and more maneuverable, but few were willing to
get close enough to inflict any significant damage
and so only one Spanish ship was taken in these
initial clashes. In the days that followed
the Spanish continued to advance eastwards
through the Channel, eventually anchoring off
the north coast of France. This was the sign for
the English to move. On the 29th of July, Raleigh,
Drake and others oversaw the launching of numerous
fireships at the Spanish Armada in the middle of
the night. These were small ships set on fire
and effectively used as primitive rockets.
The attack was enough to force the Spanish away
from the French coast without having rendezvoued
with the main land army. The weather took over
from there as an unseasonable storm suddenly
ripped through the Channel and scattered the
Spanish fleet northwards into the North Sea.
The English pursued the fleeing Spanish ships
north, but in the ensuing severe weather
many Spanish ships were wrecked off
the coasts of Scotland and Ireland,
with less than a third of the original
Armada, eventually limping home to Spain.
On land, news of this miraculous storm only
arrived gradually. Therefore, on the 8th of
August, Elizabeth rode out to review her troops
at Tilbury, who were mustering to defend England,
under the command of the Earl of
Leicester. There, dressed in white
and wearing a magnificent silver breastplate,
she gave the most famous speech of her reign:
“I am come…to live and die amongst you all –
to lay down for my God, and for my kingdoms,
and for my people, my honour and my blood,
even in the dust. I know I have the body of
a weak and feeble woman; but I have the heart and
stomach of a king – and of a King of England too,
and think foul scorn that…any prince of Europe
should dare to invade the borders of my realm…I
myself will take up arms – I
myself will be your general,
judge, and rewarder of every one
of your virtues in the field.”
The troops cheered in response to this
heartening speech from the Queen and made ready,
little knowing that they were already safe and
that the Spanish Armada had been destroyed in
the winds of the North Sea. There would be other
armadas sent by both Spain and England against one
another in a war which would last until 1604,
but the armada of 1588 has become infamous,
as it could well have resulted in the conquest
of England by Spain had it not been for the storm
which destroyed it and the calculated actions
of Elizabeth’s sea captains in the Channel.
Some historians have referred to
Elizabeth’s remaining years following 1588,
as the “second reign.” England’s economy began
to suffer due to the costs of war with Spain,
taxes mounted and prices rose as the country
experienced a series of poor harvests.
Additionally, by the 1590s, most of Elizabeth’s
old guard of advisors, courtiers, and friends
were dead and gone, their positions taken over
by a younger generation of ambitious courtiers.
Leicester died just weeks after the defeat of the
Armada in 1588. Walsingham passed two years later.
Cecil survived down to 1598, though he had
begun to pass his responsibilities to his son,
Robert, years before that. By then the queen was
an aging woman, surrounded by courtiers who played
up to her ideas of courtly love, but secretly
rolled their eyes at her aged ways in private,
criticising her seeming unwillingness to allow
the party of war hawks led by Robert Devereux,
second Earl of Essex, to take the war to Spain
more aggresively. Even in old age, Elizabeth was
unwilling to finance such a costly approach.
Meanwhile, a factional conflict developed
at the English court between Essex and Robert
Cecil, each side acquiring their own allies.
There was one area where costs spiralled utterly
in the 1590s. In 1593 the lords of Ulster,
led by Hugh O’Neill, second earl of Tyrone,
and Hugh O’Donnell, lord of Tyrconnell,
launched a new massive rebellion against
the English crown. They felt they had little
option except to do this in the face of an
ever-expanding English state in Ireland.
The Nine Years’ War would pose the greatest
existential threat to English rule yet seen
in Ireland, as O’Neill had armed his men with
guns and trained them in modern military tactics.
The Irish also sought aid from Spain and a Spanish
expedition would even arrive to Kinsale in the
south of the country in 1601. By then the Irish
were in charge of the vast majority of the island,
having inflicted the biggest defeat against
an English army there under the Tudors at
the Battle of the Yellow Ford on the 14th of
August 1598. In the end, Elizabeth would have
to finance the provision of an enormous army for
Ireland in the late 1590s and early 1600s, over
15,000 men at its height, in order to avoid the
English being expelled from the island altogether.
Her cost-saving measures here over the years
had ultimately cost her money in the long run.
The final blow emotionally for Elizabeth was a
betrayal by Essex, her newest court favourite,
a stepson of Leicester’s and in some ways
his successor in her affections. In his
early twenties, handsome and brash, the young Earl
felt no shame in taking liberties with the Queen,
who was both flattered and indulgent with
him. She gifted him monopolies on wine imports
and continually appointed him to military
positions. Elizabeth sent Essex to
Ireland to crush the rebellion there in 1599,
supported by an army of an unprecedented size.
She was enraged when he met secretly with
the leader of the Irish rebels, Hugh O’Neill,
just a few months after arriving in Ireland and
then left again for England without leave to do so
and having accomplished nothing there. When he
burst into Elizabeth’s private chambers upon
his return to London, the queen determined that
these offences could not stand. She stripped him
of his offices and priveleges and ostracised him
from court when she learned that Essex had spoken
publicly afterwards of seeing her without her
wig and her layers of poisonous make-up. Essex
was placed under house arrest and deprived of his
monopolies. In desperation, in February 1601, he
sought to lead an insurrection against Elizabeth,
not to depose her, but to extract concessions from
her and force the removal of his great rival,
Robert Cecil. However, he was unable to attract
enough support to be successful, and was executed
for treason on the 25th of February 1601.
Essex’s death seemed to drain the
last of Elizabeth’s energies from her.
By then, the Queen was growing older and weaker
all the time, and it fell to Robert Cecil,
now Elizabeth’s chief minister and the undisputed
head of the government after he had orchestrated
Essex’s destruction, to oversee a subtle
resolution of the succession question.
He knew that if Elizabeth had thus far refused to
name a successor, she was not going to do so now.
Hence, Cecil entered into secret negotiations with
King James VI of Scotland, the son of Mary Queen
of Scots. James was now well into his thirties and
a successful king in his own right in Scotland.
He was also a firm Protestant and he remained
the nearest claimant to the English throne.
From England, Cecil advised him of the
manner by which he should write to Elizabeth,
to put her in the best frame of mind to name him
as her heir. James listened well and his overtures
were received warmly by the Queen. Elizabeth
would never formally name him as her heir,
but she was more than aware in her final
years that unless she named somebody else,
the throne would inevitably fall to
her Scottish cousin once she died.
Thus, in her own strange way, Elizabeth had made
preparations for the end of the House of Tudor and
the rise of the House of Stuart to unite England
and Scotland under one king, something which
successive English monarchs of the medieval era
had failed to achieve through force of arms.
In March 1603, Elizabeth fell seriously ill.
She was nearing her seventieth year by then.
Suffering from a fever and from
sores in her mouth and throat,
Cecil urged her to take to her sickbed, saying she
must rest. “Little man,” she snapped back at him,
“must is not a word to use to princes,” showing
that even at the end she was still a force to be
reckoned with. She died in her bed at Richmond
Palace not long after this, on the morning of
the 24th of March 1603. She was 69 years old and
had ruled England for forty-four and a half years.
Besides her few mementoes of Leicester and her
other loved ones, a locket ring was found among
the Queen’s few obviously sentimental possessions.
The ring opened to reveal two tiny miniatures,
one of Elizabeth and one of another young
woman dressed in a much older Tudor fashion.
Historians theorize that the woman featured in
the second miniature was her mother, Anne Boleyn.
Elizabeth had never known her, Anne having been
executed on her father’s orders when Elizabeth
was just two years old. But her untimely
death had hung like a shadow over Elizabeth,
dictating many of her choices, notably
her unwillingness over almost two decades
to order the execution of Mary Queen of
Scots, and her own decision to never marry.
In the weeks following Elizabeth’s death, James VI
and his Scottish entourage made their way south at
a leisurely pace, meeting his new subjects along
the way. Cecil had put everything in place and
James was crowned in Westminster Abbey on the 25th
of July 1603 as James I of England and Ireland
and VI of Scotland. In Ireland, the injection
of thousands of troops and the appointment
of an effective military commander to oversee
affairs there, Charles Blount, Lord Mountjoy,
had seen O’Neill and his Irish confederates
defeated in the spring of 1603. Tyrone surrendered
a week after Elizabeth’s death, believing she was
still alive, though James ultimately offered very
lenient peace terms. With the war over in Ireland,
and both Elizabeth and her Spanish nemesis,
Philip II, dead, the pathway to peace opened up
and the Treaty of London in 1604 brought the First
Anglo-Spanish War to an end. It was something of
a stalemate, but given that England had survived
war with the superpower of the sixteenth century,
it was very much an English victory. The reign
that followed would see many of the projects which
Elizabeth’s reign had commenced come to fruition,
with the first English colonies settled in
North America at Jamestown in Virginia in 1607
and in New England from 1620 onwards. England
would remain a Protestant state therafter.
Elizabeth I was a very complicated
woman. During a long reign of 45 years,
she presided over one of the most
important periods in English history.
When she rose to the throne England was in a
confused state, toing and froing over and back
between Roman Catholicism and Protestantism, while
as a state within Europe England had declined
enormously from being one of the most centralised
and powerful kingdoms of medieval Europe
to becoming something of a minnow in the fifteenth
century, wracked by instability and civil war.
All of that changed during Elizabeth’s
reign. The duration of it allowed for the
firm establishment of the country as a moderate
Protestant power, while her long confronatation
with Spain reasserted England as a force
to be reckoned with in European politics.
The small kingdom effectively defeated Spain, the
superpower of the day, in the Anglo-Spanish War
and provided crucial support to the Dutch rebels
in the early days of their war of independence.
Ireland was about to be reduced fully to English
rule and while the first permanent English
colonies were not settled in the Caribbean and
North America until the reign of her successor,
King James I, the groundwork was
firmly laid during Elizabeth’s reign.
And yet there were strange elements to her time as
queen. She was a woman who was haunted by the fate
her mother had suffered at the hands of her father
and who spent much of her life prevaricating over
both the prospect of marrying and removing
the threat posed by Mary Queen of Scots.
In the end, there is no doubt that her reign
was a success, though its success was owing as
much to figures like Drake, Raleigh, Cecil and
Walsingham as it was to queen herself.
What do you think of Queen Elizabeth I?
Was she truly England’s greatest queen,
or have historians simply lionized her because
of successes which were achieved during her reign
which had little to do with her
own role as ruler of the realm?
Please let us know in the comment section, and in
the meantime, thank you very much for watching!